Cambridge, MA

+1-(857) 600-9490

David_Bellamy@g.harvard.edu P

PhD Candidate in Medical Machine Learning

Personal website LinkedIn: drbellamy Twitter: DavidRBellamy

I am a PhD candidate in my final year of Epidemiology and Biostatistics at the Harvard School of Public Health. In my PhD, I have developed deep learning methods for risk prediction in the intensive care unit as well as for causal inference in the presence of unmeasured confounding. In the past, I spent 6 years conducting research in molecular biology across several topics. You can read more about me on my personal website!

SKILLS

Communication English, French

Natural Sciences Molecular biology, (epi)genetics

Quantitative Sciences Deep learning, causal inference, statistics

Tools and Languages Python (TF/Keras, PyTorch, Pandas, Numpy, etc.), R (tidyverse), Cloud (Azure)

Git, Makefile, Slurm, Bash/Linux, ŁTĘX, MarkDown, SQL, unit testing, OOP

EDUCATION

Doctor of Philosophy in Epidemiology, Harvard UniversitySep 2018 — PresentMasters of Science in Biostatistics, Harvard UniversitySep 2018 — PresentDoctor of Philosophy in Biomedical Science, Harvard UniversitySep 2016 — Jan 2018 (left)Honours Bachelor of Science in Biochemistry, University of Ottawa, summa cum laudeSep 2011 — May 2016

PUBLICATIONS

Published Articles

Deep Learning Methods for Proximal Inference via Maximum Moment Restriction

2022

NeurIPS 2022 Main Conference, Preprint here: arXiv

- Ben Kompa*, David Bellamy*, Tom Kolokotrones, James Robins, Andrew L. Beam.
- * Denotes equal contribution.

A structural characterization of shortcut features for prediction

2022

European Journal of Epidemiology, Paper here

• David Bellamy, Miguel Hernan, Andrew L. Beam.

Evaluating Progress on Machine Learning for Longitudinal Electronic Healthcare Data

2020

Preprint here: arXiv

- David Bellamy, Leo Celi, Andrew L. Beam.
- Under preparation for submission to a conference.

Charity Care: Do Nonprofit Hospitals Give More than For-Profit Hospitals?

2020

Journal of General Internal Medicine, Paper here

· Joseph D. Bruch, David Bellamy.

Reciprocal cellular cross-talk within the tumor microenvironment promotes oncolytic virus activity

2015

Nature Medicine, Paper here

Carolina S Ilkow, Monique Marguerie, Cory Batenchuk, Justin Mayer, Daniela Ben Neriah, Sophie Cousineau, Theresa Falls,
 Victoria A Jennings, Meaghan Boileau, David Bellamy, et al.

Manuscripts under Preparation

Extending Transformers to massive laboratory datasets in electronic health records

2022

Target journal: Nature Digital Medicine

- David Bellamy, Bhawesh Kumar, Cindy Wang, Andrew L. Beam.
- My first dissertation paper, coming soon.

Minimax optimization of the proximal inference bridge function

2023

Target conference: ICLR 2023

• David Bellamy*, Tom Kolokotrones*, James Robins, Andrew L. Beam.

Theoretical equivalence between the Transport algorithm and a simple set of graphical criteria

2023

Target conference: IJCAI 2023

· David Bellamy, James Robins.

+1-(857) 600-9490 Cambridge, MA

David_Bellamy@g.harvard.edu PhD Candidate in Medical Machine Learning

Personal website LinkedIn: drbellamy Twitter: DavidRBellamy

PolyMed: a massively multimodal Transformer for electronic health records

Target conference: ICML 2023

• David Bellamy*, Anil Panepu*, Andrew L. Beam.

HONORS & AWARDS

2nd place in the Harvard LISH datathon

Feb 2022

2023

 Placed second out of 60 teams from top US institutions doing a binary prediction task. Our solution used an ensemble of random forest and XGBoost models.

\$1500 McMahon Fund Jan 2022

Awarded to attend a technical causal inference workshop at The Simons Institute, Theory of Computing.

\$60,000 UCB Pharma Fellowship

2021 - Present

Selected as the recipient by the Department of Epidemiology, to support the remainder of my PhD.

First place \$1000 prize at Connecting Young Minds

2015

• Won first place at the University of Ottawa's research presentation competition by popular vote.

Canada's \$8000 NSERC-USRA

2013 & 2015

• The Canadian Natural Sciences and Engineering Council offers undergraduate student research awards to top applicants.

I conducted two summers of research with this funding.

OHRI's Best Summer Student Researcher

2014

The Ottawa Hospital Research Institute awarded \$500 to the most promising student.

J. Armand Bombardier \$4000 Scholarship for Research Abroad

2014

I moved to Boston in the fall of 2014 to conduct epigenetics research at Harvard Medical School.

First place at Healthcare Symposium

2014

• The University of Ottawa held a research presentation competition for healthcare.

Merit scholarship for exceptional standing

2012 - 2016

• The University of Ottawa awarded this to undergraduates in the top percentile of the grade distribution.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

PhD Candidate with Drs. Andrew Beam and Miguel Hernan

July 2020 — Present

Harvard School of Public Health

Cambridge, MA

- Completing my dissertation research in the Harvard CAUSALab.
- Developing novel deep learning architectures better-suited for medical data.
- Currently extending the Transformer model to handle continuous data.
- Also developing applications of deep learning algorithms in causal inference with Dr. James Robins.

PhD student with Dr. Elise Robinson

Sep 2018 — July 2020

Stanley Center for Psychiatric Research at Broad Institute

Boston, MA

- Began my PhD here, working on a massive factor analysis of the UK BioBank's questionnaire data.
- Modelled factor scores for each patient as a function of genetic markers.
- This permitted the discovery of novel SNPs associated with latent constructs like depression and anxiety.

PhD student with Dr. Eric Greer / Heritable epigenetics

Sep 2016 — Dec 2016

Boston, MA

- Harvard Medical School
- Studied regulators of DNA methylation and how they influence transgenerational gene expression.
 Developed a screening assay using biochemical fractionation and an HPLC-MS methylation assay to discover new regulators.
- Performed a knock-out screen in *C. elegans* to assess transgenerational phenotypes.

Researcher with Dr. Kathryn Wright / Virology

Sep 2015 — May 2016

University of Ottawa

Ottawa, Canada

• Studied curcumin's inhibition of the HPIV3 virus's replication.

Researcher with Dr. Daniel Figeys / Mass spectrometry

Ottawa Institute of Systems Biology

May 2015 — Aug 2015 Ottawa, Canada

Ottawa, Canada

 Developed a mass spec.-based technique for identifying novel low molecular weight peptides in the hypothalamus and hippocampus of Mus musculus for applications to human disease profiling.

+1-(857) 600-9490 Cambridge, MA David_Bellamy@g.harvard.edu

PhD Candidate in Medical Machine Learning

Personal website LinkedIn: drbellamy Twitter: DavidRBellamy

Researcher with Dr. Yang Shi / Epigenetics

Boston Children's Hospital

Sep 2014 — **Dec 2014** *Boston, MA*

- Studied the epigenetic factors in the myeloid differentiation block in acute myeloid leukemia.
- Conducted high-throughput RNAi and chemical inhibitor screens of chromatin-regulating enzymes.
- Followed up the screen with CRISPR knockouts of promising candidates.

Researcher with Dr. John Bell / Viral cancer therapy

Ottawa Hospital Research Institute

Jan 2014 — Aug 2014

- Ottawa, Canada
- Conducted a high-throughput RNAi screen of a virus library in search of enhancer miRNAs.
- Cloned candidate miRNAs into clinically approved oncolytic viruses (VSV & MG-1).
- Performed in vitro and in vivo testing of cloned viruses.

Researcher with Dr. Darrin Richeson / Inorganic chemistry

Chemistry department, University of Ottawa

May 2013 — Sep 2013

Ottawa, Canada

- Designed the synthesis of a high molecular weight ligand, capable of binding Rhenium ions.
- The Rhenium-ligand complex was tested for its capacity to reduce CO_2 to formic acid when stimulated by UV.

MENTORSHIP EXPERIENCE

Cindy Wang / Harvard Undergraduate in CS & Pre-Med

June 2021 — Present

- Held weekly meetings from her freshman year onwards.
- We are currently collaborating on a deep learning project.

Bhawesh Kumar / Harvard MSc student in Health Data Science

Sep 2021 — Present

- · Held weekly meetings throughout his MSc.
- We are currently collaborating on a deep learning project.

Michael Smith / Harvard MSc student in Epidemiology

Sep 2021 — Present

- Held monthly meetings throughout his MSc.
- I help formalize his research interests in causality and machine learning.

Denys Shay / Harvard PhD student in Epidemiology

Sep 2021 - Present

- I am his assigned "epi buddy."
- I have helped him pick courses for the first 2 years of his PhD in Epidemiology.

Zhaoxun Hou / Harvard MSc student in Epidemiology

Sep 2021 - Present

- · I am his assigned "epi buddy."
- I have helped him pick courses and prepare applications to Biostatistics PhD programs.

Sarthak Agarwal / Matriculating PhD student in Nutritional Epidemiology

Oct 2021 — Present

I edited his application to the HSPH PhD program and he was accepted.

Brandon Spiegel / Data Scientist at Qventus

Oct 2021 — Present

• A data scientist in the private sector who I have educated on causality, ML and graduate education.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Deep Learning Teaching Fellow

March 2022 — May 2022

Harvard EPI290 / BMI707

- Worked as a teaching fellow with Drs. Andrew Beam and Kun-Hsing Yu in the main course on deep learning at the Harvard Medical campus.
- This course used Tensorflow/Keras.

Epidemiology Department Tutor

Feb 2022 — May 2022

Harvard School of Public Health

 Tutored Masters students in Epidemiology for statistics, learning R, and the core epidemiologic methods courses (EPI201/202/289/203/204).

Epidemiology & Biostatistics Teaching Fellow

June 2021 — Aug 2021

Harvard ID207 & ID208

- Assisted Drs. Brian Healy and Pamela Rist in the full-time summer foundations course for the Masters of Public Health in Epidemiology.
- Led programming tutorials for students to learn how to analyze data with STATA.

+1-(857) 600-9490 Cambridge, MA David_Bellamy@g.harvard.edu

PhD Candidate in Medical Machine Learning

Personal website LinkedIn: drbellamy Twitter: DavidRBellamy

Jan 2016 - April 2016

Biochemistry Teaching Fellow (French)

University of Ottawa BCH2333

• Gave sections for the core second year class in Biochemistry in French (150 students).

ACTIVITIES

Journal reviewer

• Nature Communications, Nature Scientific Data, uOttawa Journal of Medicine.

Harvard student mental health representative

• Assisted Dr. Paul Barreira in tailoring a mental health survey to the Population Health Sciences PhD students.

Biochemistry curriculum representative

- Provided perspectives on biochemistry learning objectives and course content.
- Participated in redesigning the undergraduate biochemistry curriculum at the University of Ottawa.
- Helped create a more research-focused biochemistry degree.